So today's דף *daf* is ל''ט *lamed tet*, 39, and we start
top of the דף *daf* and we spent a few pages dealing
with the issue of מצה matzah, *matzah* both in terms of it
has a special status like, you know, מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni *ma'aser
sheni* and also a lot of discussions about what constitutes לחם *lechem*
and issue specific about לחם עוני Lechem Oni *lechem oni*, general issues
about לחם *lechem*, comparing it to questions about חלה *challah* and things
that have the ability of becoming חמץ chametz *chametz*, מי פירות *mei
peirot*, what rice, etc. Now we turn to perhaps a more narrow
discussion about מרור Maror? *maror*. So let's take a look top of
ל''ט עמוד א' *lamed tet amud aleph*. ואלו ירקות yerakot שאדם יוצא
בהן ידי חובתו בפסח *ve'eilu yerakot she'adam yotzei bahen yedei chovato bapesach*.
These are the vegetables you fulfill your obligation for פסח Pesach, *Pesach*
specifically for the מצווה *mitzvah* of מרור Maror *maror*. בחזרת, bachazeret בתמכא,
B'tamcha, ובחרחבינא, ובעולשין, ובמרור *bechazeret, betamcha, uvecharchevina,
uva'ulshin, uvemaror*. Okay, so these five vegetables, interesting there's like a comparison
maybe to the five grains, how we know that you have five
vegetables or that that satisfy is interesting. I'll just say at the
outset, you know that the תורה Torah *Torah* does say על מצות
ומרורים al matzot u'merorim *al matzos u'merorim*. So מרורים merorim, *merorim* in
the plural, you know, reasonable interpretation is like, bitter herbs with more
than one leaf, well
no, but anyway with that's not specifically identifying a particular type of
vegetable, like it's a category of things that are bitter. So the
משנה Mishnah. *Mishna* here understands that there are five different things. What
exactly they are we will see in the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*. חזרת
chazeret.
*chazeret* I should mention is something that we normally interpret to be
a type of lettuce. So we will see anyway as the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* tries to identify it. I wonder if I have not
checked, I wonder if the ArtScroll actually gives an identification or not.
We'll talk about that when we read the people who have the
ArtScroll since, you know, can tell me what they say, we'll see
that when we get to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Steinsaltz gives, okay,
so I mean Steinsaltz, so we'll see when we get to the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* to so I'll call on you to share that.
יוצאין בהן *yotzin bahen*, you fulfill obligation with them, בין לחין lachin
בין יבשין *bein lachin bein yeveshim*, whether they are moist or dry,
אבל aval, לא lo, כבושה *aval lo k'vusha*, not pickled, because presumably
if they're pickled it changes their taste and it would not be
a bitter taste anymore.
Would it be more bitter or less bitter?
Or are things that are pickled bitter?
Sour, salty, anyway it's from the outside, it overwhelms their own taste
certainly. ולא שלוקין ולא מבושלים v'lo mevushalim *velo shelukin velo mevushalim*, not
שלוקין *shelukin* which is like, you know, double cooked, cooked to the
point of it's almost sort of dissolving and not cooked, all these
things presumably significantly change their taste. ולא מבושלים *velo mevushalim*, yeah, ומצטרפין
לכזית *umitzstarfin lekezayit*, and you can have a little bit of different
ones and all combined they make a כזית kezayis *kezayit*. You don't
need one כזית kezayis *kezayit* of any particular one. ויוצאין בקלח שלהם
*veyotzin beklach shelahem*, you fulfill your obligation with their stalk, not just
with their leaves. ובדמאי *ubidmai*, and now the end of it sounds
like our משנה Mishnah. *mishna* by מצה matzah *matzah*, ובדמאי *ubidmai*, you
can do it with if it's מרור maror, *maror* that you're not
certain if תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'ma'asros *terumot u'ma'asrot* has been taken from,
which is דמאי *demai* status. ובמעשר ראשון שנטלה תרומתו *ubema'aser rishon shenitla
terumato*, or first מעשר ma'aser *ma'aser* that the תרומה *teruma* has been
taken from that the לוי *Levi* gives to the כהן *Kohen*. ומעשר
שני והקדש שנפדו *uma'aser sheni vehekdesh shenifdu*, or מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni
*ma'aser sheni* הקדש *hekdesh* that have been redeemed. Okay, so that's what
we've seen parallel to מצה matzah. *matzah*, there's not going to be
too much to say about the end except to point out that
by these things, the obligation of תרומות ומעשרות *terumot u'ma'asrot*, the obligation
of of
so that's דמאי *demai*, מעשר ma'aser ראשון *ma'aser rishon*, and מעשר שני
Ma'aser Sheni *ma'aser sheni* is all rabbinic because it's vegetables.
So will that make a difference? Anyway, here we're being lenient, you
know, we're giving we're saying it's permissible, but just to keep in
mind that at most it's anyway a rabbinic status. Let's take a
look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* as it tries to identify what
these are. חזרת chazeret היא חסא chasa, *chazeret hi chasa*, which normally
of course is lettuce. Now רש''י Rashi *Rashi* says, I don't know
old French, letuga, so I have no idea. It has to L-T,
so maybe it does mean lettuce.
Yes, that's according to Koren, as the Latin name Lactuca sativa is
the term for lettuce.
Oh, letuga, so you have the L-T-C, letuga lettuce. Old French from
the Latin. Okay, does ArtScroll say anything interesting here?
No, it just transliterates חסא chasa, *chasa*.
Wonderful. עולשין ulshin *ulshin* says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is הינדבי *hindivi*.
So again, רש''י Rashi *Rashi* says it's some type of a weed
or grass or herb called krispula, which I have no idea. What
does Koren says?
Cichorium endivia, endive.
This is based on a translation of רש''י Rashi *Rashi*, right? Based
on רש''י Rashi *Rashi*'s word krispula or based on the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s word הינדבי *hindivi*?
Probably, it doesn't say, but endive and הינדבי *hindivi* are very similar
words. So yeah, what does that say?
Yeah, here same thing, says either endives or chicory which is what
endive is when grown underground or escarole which is the same
species.
Okay, interesting, endive. Tamcha תמכא. Tamcha? So what's Tamcha תמכא? Tamcha אמר
רבה בר בר חנה תמכתא שמה. Amar Rabba Bar Bar Chana Tamchata
shema. Okay, well that was helpful. Okay, so רש"י Rashi says מרוביא.
Maruvya. Okay, so what do we have there for Koren, what does
he do?
Horseradish. Oh, really? Yeah, that's interesting. I think that's—is that modern Hebrew
for horseradish? No.
But that's not a root plant, horseradish is.
Horseradish is a root, isn't it?
Okay, what does Artscroll say?
Well, here they
say—they say two things. Horehound, which is חורי רוש לענה, Chorei Rosh
Lana, they didn't translate that as horehound, I'm not sure what that
is, but Artscroll also says that it's the same idea as what
we were saying, horseradish.
Okay, so which
one are we on now?
Okay, תמכא Tamcha we just did. Okay, so תמכא tamcha, at least
to English translations, I don't know basing themselves on רש"י Rashi or
what, seem to be identifying it in the category of horseradish. Okay,
חרחבינא. Charchavina. Now what's חרחבינא? Charchavina? אמר רבי שמעון לקיש אצבתא דדיקלא.
Amar Rabbi Shimon Lakish Atzvata d'dikla. Some type of a vine that
grows around a palm tree. Okay, so I don't know if they
give more specific identification.
Yes. Koren appears to disagree and say plant called
Eryngium creticum, a perennial plant found throughout Israel. There's a picture of
it.
And so what does the דיקלא dikla part of that word mean?
The palm tree. He doesn't know.
But he translated it as palm tree.
Oh, but does it look like—but does it look like—it doesn't
look like a palm tree.
It looks like—it doesn't look like a vine around a palm tree.
What does it look like? Some type of a lettuce-type plant?
No, it's just a flower. Okay.
Anything from Rabbi Scroll there? No. Kind of a palm tree. All
right. במרור. B'Maror. Now what's מרור? maror, מרור maror. is מריריתא, Meririta,
which also doesn't help too much. רש"י Rashi says אמפוריא, Ampurya, which
I again have no idea what that is, and oh, then רש"י
Rashi says helpfully Vipupres, so that—there you go. So what does—again, if
I knew more Old French. Yes.
Common sow thistle Sonchus oleraceus from the Asteraceae family.
That was so helpful.
It's a flower.
A flower? Oh God, okay.
What is—I'm not sure what this is, a burdock, which is a
plant with prickly flowers and large leaves. He says ארוכא, Arocha, that's
what—this is some sort of wild lettuce.
All right, so anyway, so we don't know. Okay, moving on, I'm
glad we cleared that off. Okay, anyway, lettuce and endive certainly seems
to be in here, and issues like horseradish maybe, but it's so—again,
and that gets to the issue, you know, when I was... What?
He said the horseradish is a root vegetable, but these East European,
these were more...
It's interesting, they didn't have lettuce in אשכנז? Ashkenaz? I don't know.
Maybe at
that time.
I don't know. All I know is growing up, all I know
is when I was like under 10 years old, everybody had horseradish.
And then at some stage the rabbis started saying, right, oh you
know, according to the גמרא, Gemara it's clear that actually lettuce or
Romaine lettuce or different types of lettuce are really—and now, right, and
now you have the whole issue of bugs. Anyway, now I see
that it's very widespread that people do both Romaine lettuce and you
know and horseradish.
Yeah,
right, maybe. Okay, let's keep on going. Let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. תני בר קפרא, Tani Bar Kappara, so בר קפרא Bar
Kappara taught, אלו ירקות שאדם יוצא בהן ידי חובתו בפסח. Eilu yerakot
she'adam yotzei bahen yedei hovato b'Pesach. Here are the vegetables. באולשין, B'ulshin,
which is in our משנה. Mishnah. בתמכא, b'tamcha which is in our
משנה. Mishnah בחרחלין, B'charchalin, that was not our משנה. Mishnah, Our משנה
Mishnah did not have חרחלין, charchalin, it had חרחבינין, charchavinin,
which is in our משנה, mishna, ובחזרת. u'v'chazeret. So everything was in
our משנה mishna, except what he didn't mention was מרור, maror? okay,
and what he added was חרחלין. charchalin. So maybe that was a
different name for מרור, maror. maybe he disagrees about that fifth plant.
רבי יהודה אומר אף אולשי שדי ואולשי גינה. Rabbi Yehuda omer Af
ulshei sadei v'ulshei gina. You can even fulfill your obligation with these
אולשין, ulshin, which is again some type of a—I don't know—some type
of a plant, some type of a vegetable.
This is endives.
Oh, we're back to the endive. Oh, oh yeah, I'm sorry, that
is what the גמרא Gemara said, אולשין הינדבי. ulshin is hindvi. Okay,
so let's translate it for now as endives. Whether they are wild
endives or whether they are domesticated, whether they are farmed
endives and וחזרת. v'chazeret. So now what did he add? We already
said אולשין ulshin and חזרת. chazeret So he seemed to add that
it didn't matter whether it was אולשי שדי ulshei sadei or אולשי
גינה. ulshei gina. So that's what גמרא Gemara says, אולשי גינה וחזרת
תנא להו רישא. ulshei gina v'chazeret tana lei reisha. So your standard
endives presumably are those that are gardened and חזרת chazeret we said
explicitly. So why did he say those two? The only thing he
really added was אולשי שדי, ulshei sadei, was this wild endive. So
the גמרא Gemara says: הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, yeah that is what
he means. He means אף אולשי שדי, af ulshei sadei, even wild
endives are כאולשי גינה וחזרת, k'ulshei gina v'chazeret, are just as good
as you know as domesticated endives and as חזרת chazeret and as
lettuce. So yeah, but what he added was even the wild variety
is included. רבי מאיר אומר אף אצבתא וטורא ומר ירור. Rabbi Meir
omer Af atzvata v'tura u'mar yeruar. So even these three things. You
got me. אמר ליה רבי יוסי... Amar lei Rabbi Yossi...
Oh, I just—מר ירור mar yeruar is o-p-a-m-p-a-c-k... ronium, a perennial plant
from the shrub family which grows wild in Lebanon and Northern Israel.
Okay, so some type of a shrub or something. All right. So
אמר ליה רבי יוסי, amar lei Rabbi Yose, so Rabbi Yose said
to it, עשבת ויתורא אחד הוא, asvat vitura echad hu, they're the
same thing. ומר, u'mar, ומר זהו ירואר u'mar zehu yeruar and now
this is our version. And the bitter thing, that's ירואר yeruar which
maybe means that it's identifying it with מרור. maror? If you look
at the side, the side has a different גירסא girsa which is
אף עשבת ויתורא חד הוא, af asvat vitura chad hu, it's sharp
or maybe it's one. Okay, ומר הוא u'mar hu and it's bitter.
וזהו מר ירואר vezehu mar yeruar and it's the same as מר
ירואר. mar yeruar. It just says all three are the same thing.
Okay, תני דבי שמואל, tani d'vei Shmuel, we taught in the house
of Shmuel, אלו ירקות שאדם יוצא בהן ידי חובתו בפסח, eilu yerakot
she'adam yotzei vahen yedei chovato b'Pesach, the following things you fulfill your
obligation:
בחזרת which we said, בעולשין b'olshin which we said, בתמכא which we
also said, all those three so far are in the משנה, mishna
right? The first two we've now we've said are some type of
a lettuce and endives. You have תמכא, חרחבינא charchavina which we said,
ובחרגינין, u'vcharginnin,
חרגינין charginnin which is not in our משנה, Mishnah but it was
added in the—no, it wasn't added in the ברייתא. braita. The ברייתא
braita beforehand had חרחבילין charchavilin and this is חרגינין, charginnin, so that's
a new one.
Here they're saying it's oregano.
Oregano, oh that's interesting. Oregano. You see the same sort of—you see
the same letters as it were. Oregano, that's interesting. Oregano is מרור?
maror, Okay, well we have the oregano spice. I don't know what
the oregano plant would taste like.
Paula has it in her garden.
Yeah, what does it taste like?
It's a little plant. It tastes like oregano, the spice.
Oh it does? Okay. ובהרדופנין u'vehardofnin and with הרדופנין hardofnin which we
will—also is new. And any translations of that?
Nope. Here they're saying רש''י Rashi says it's some sort of wormwood,
like again, Scorzonera hispanica. He's saying the ערוך Aruch says it's oleander.
Oleander. Okay. All right. So,
wasn't he the guy that made the wands in Harry Potter? No,
that was somebody else. Who was that? That was anyway, what? Ollivander.
Sorry. Okay. רבי יהודה אומר אף חזרת יולין וחזרת גלין. Rabbi Yehuda
omer af chazeret yulin v'chazeret galin. So he says two types of
חזרת chazeret also, two subspecies: חזרת יולין chazeret yulin and חזרת גלין.
chazeret galin. So I don't know exactly what those are. If I
knew what חזרת chazeret. was, but anyway we're assuming חזרת chazeret is
a lettuce, so two types of subspecies.
Yeah, but now they're saying that he's saying just those specific subspecies?
No, even those are included in חזרת. chazeret כיוצא בהן keyotzei vahen
are just as good as the—you know that's what כיוצא בהן keyotzei
vahen are just as good as, you know, are like everything else
you just mentioned. Okay, so we have added this—this חרגינין charginnin which
we said might be oregano, and הרדופנין hardofnin which maybe is oleander.
Okay. רבי אילא אומר משום רבי אליעזר אף ארקבלים. Rabbi Ila omer
mishum Rabbi Eliezer af arkavalim. אף ארקבלים, af arkavalim, even this spice
called ארקבלים. arkavalim. Go figure that. Any translations of that? Nope.
Michael, he's got a whole long note. Okay. רש''י Rashi says it's
also some type of a vine or something.
Or even the—at least the ר''ש Rash is saying it's some actual
part of the tree.
Interesting, because the גמרא's Gemara going to say later that these are
not trees, these are all plants, but okay, these are vegetables. Anyway,
let's take a look.
וחזרתי על כל תלמידיו, vechazarti al kol talmidav, I searched after all
of רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer students to find somebody who could corroborate
that I had heard this from, you know, this teaching of רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, that they had heard the same thing from him.
וביקשתי לי חבר, uvikashti li chaver, and I tried to find a
colleague, I mean I tried to find somebody who could corroborate this,
ולא מצאתי, v'lo matzati, and I did not find anybody. Nobody else
remembered רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer ever saying that you could use this
type of a plant. וכשבאתי לפני רבי אלעזר בן יעקב, ukshebati lifnei
Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov, and when I came to רבי אלעזר בן
יעקב, Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov, הודה לי לדברי, hoda li lidvarai, he
conceded to the point that that is good. Not clear whether he
conceded that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said it or he just conceded
that he agreed that that would be good for מרור. maror רבי
יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, כל
שיש לו שרף, kol sheyesh lo saraf, any type of a plant
that when you cut it, you have some type of a sap
that comes out. Presumably we're not talking about a tree, we're talking
about like again, a vegetable that there's some type of a sap.
You know, so if you cut like a lettuce leaf, you do
see some juices come out like along the spine.
Can you use a sugar maple? What? Can you use a sugar
maple?
Yes. I don't know, that would seem to be very inclusive. You
don't know—I guess what's frustrating for me besides just not knowing what
the individual things here are, is that you read all of these
things and you have no idea what criteria they're using. You know,
is it like הלכה למשה מסיני? halacha leMoshe miSinai? What constitutes מרור?
maror? Is it based on taste? Is it a particular range of
tastes and everybody's making their own—their own judgment that this falls within
those range of tastes? So now at least you're getting them trying
to identify some type of a criterion. Now it doesn't explain why
those criteria are significant. Who cares that it has sap or doesn't
have sap? Are you telling me that everything that has sap has
a bitter taste?
Right, well the
גמרא's Gemara going to
get to
that a little bit later on, but right, but like so but
yes, what are you trying to identify here?
So we think about this logically and historically, it had to be
something they could get pretty easily in Egypt because they're in a
bit of a rush. So probably something...
Well, I don't think the גמרא Gemara is trying to identify what
they had when they left Egypt. I think the גמרא's Gemara understanding
that מרורים, merorim. bitter herbs, means a category of things that satisfy
that can be called bitter. So it doesn't matter whether it was
exactly the one that they had. It's not like finding the ארבע
מינים arba minim of the לולב lulav that are very specific things
and you have to assume
that the Jews had access to it at the time or else
how could God have commanded it? Here it could be a type
of category. If I said use spices, I would whatever spices. So
this is a category called מרורים. But again, you want to know
what criteria they're using. Okay, so let's take a look. He says
something that has a type of a sap. רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא
אומר Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka omer כל שפניו מכסיפין, kol she-panav makhsifin,
anything that the face of it
is like pale. רש״י Rashi explains it, like it's not a dark
green, it's a more lighter shade. Okay, again, why is that significant?
What does that indicate?
Would it change color if you leave it out?
No, רש״י Rashi doesn't say that. רש״י Rashi says it means that
it's not a dark green like certain vegetables but it's more of
a pale of a pale color.
Like you
use a leek?
Right, exactly. That's how רש״י Rashi explains it. אחרים אומרים, Acherim omrim,
others say כל ירק מר יש לו שרף ופניו מכסיפין. kol yerek
mar yesh lo saraf u-panav makhsifin.
Now we get: anything that is bitter has both aspects, both has
a type of a sap and is a more pale type of
a vegetable. So now we at least get to... but again the
question is, so why don't they just say anything that tastes bitter?
But presumably, I'm guessing here, that taste is a very subjective experience.
So maybe they don't want to just say, figure it out yourself
if it tastes bitter it's okay. They want to give you something
more quantifiable.
So a pale look or sap is easier than what
exactly... if you ask me, is it clearly sometimes that the difference
is between sour and bitter and sharp and? So not everybody has
those types of precise ways of identifying taste, but it does seem
from this that the גמרא Gemara in the end is trying to
say, look, anything that's bitter. And we're trying to identify for you
things that we have identified constitute bitter and then trying to actually
quantify in maybe a way that's easier to measure than the criteria
of bitter is this idea of sap and pale, but he says
actually you would need both. And אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan,
so says רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, and this seems very self-evident this
statement מדברי כולן אלמד, mi-divrei kullan elmad, from all of these we
can understand ירק מר יש לו שרף ופניו מכסיפין, yerek mar yesh
lo saraf u-panav makhsifin, that bitter herbs have this sap and have
this pale and have this pale face. Now not necessarily, because just
because everything that has that is pale and has a sap is
bitter doesn't mean that everything that is bitter is pale and has
a sap. So anyway, yes, Charlie?
As I say, I've never seen sap in romaine lettuce.
I don't know, haven't tried it.
So in common parlance, don't we distinguish between what we would call
in Hebrew חריף charif and
מר?
mar? Right, sharp and bitter, right?
So horseradish is sharp. It's sharp. Right, right.
And I agree and I think that that is why because, but
again, if you ask me to exactly identify these things, is this
bitter? Or do you think this is sharp?
At a certain point I would like I really have no idea.
So I think that's why the גמרא's Gemara trying to quantify it
a little more.
I'll tell you what's bitter.
Eggplant before you drain all that juice. Okay, so eggplant juice is
bitter. No, but forget...
How about how about lemon juice? Is lemon juice bitter or sharp?
Sour. Sour.
See, sour,
bitter, sharp, to me those are all like very overlapping and close
categories.
Like horseradish is hot. Bitter isn't hot. Whether it's sour or bitter,
that's the thing we we're inclined to go for things like certainly
אשכנזים, Ashkenazim, things that are hot. That in our common parlance, that's
not bitter.
And we'll see about that more coming up.
סחוג Schug is not bitter.
It's not a good... nobody really goes for bitter.
That's a very interesting... in other words, sharp, like you have a...
like the פסח, Pesach the פסח Pesach, was right, כרוך karukh with
the מצה, matzah soft מצה matzah. and with... so that we like
that. We like meat with something that's hot. But nobody would put
bitter. The question is what מר...
mar... right? I think that's excellent and I do think that that's
why because of these differences of bitter and sour and sharp or
whatever, that's my understanding why the גמרא Gemara is trying to identify
it in a way that at least for them... if you know
what these words mean, at least it's more identifiable. You don't have
to start figuring out is this bitter or is this sour. Just
get the food. Yeah, exactly. And that's and here even when we
give criteria it's criteria I think that are a little bit more
measurable.
I'm saying that if I were to find a vegetable that's not
bitter but did have the sap and this pale green color that'd
be okay? Does it have to be bitter?
Right, so I don't, yeah, so I it doesn't seem to be
that point. It seems to be that the argument is, okay, although
it is true that אחרים Acherim says רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yohanan said
that as long as it's pale you know it's going to be
okay, you know it'll be bitter, or רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said
that as long as it has sap you know it's going to
be okay. אחרים Acherim said the same thing רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yohanan
said, anything that is bitter has those two, which doesn't necessarily mean
that if it has those two it's bitter.
Anyway, where can I find something that's not bitter that has?
Presumably not, but presumably the point גמרא Gemara is trying to tell
you if it has those criteria then it will be bitter. אמר
רב יהודה הלכה כאחרים, Amar Rav Yehuda Halakha ke-Acherim,
we rule like אחרים, Acherim, we rule like those that say that
this is a great way of identifying it if it's both if
it has sap and it is pale. רבינא, Ravina, okay, so, now,
now we've done with the criteria and identifying various things, now we
have a little story. רבינא אשכחיה לרב אחא בריה דרבא, Ravina ashchelei
l'Rav Acha brei d'Rava, רבינא Ravina found רב אחא Rav Acha the
son of רבא Rava דהוה מהדר אמריסה. de-havei mehader amari'sa. He was
looking for the מרור, maror, the fifth one mentioned, the
מריסה, marisa, okay, which might even be something more like sharp, more
like horseradish. אמר ליה, Amar lei, anyway it was the bottom thing
at the list and it's called מרו. maru. אמר ליה: Amar lei:
מאי דעתך? Mai da'atach? What made you want to find specifically that
one?
דמרירין טפי? Di-meririn tfei? You picked it because that was more bitter
than everything else on the list? וחזרת תנן? Ve-chazeret nan? But חזרת
chazeret is the first one on the list! And there's an assumption
that the first one is probably the preferred one. ותנא דבי שמואל
חזרת, Ve-tana d'vei Shmuel chazeret, and if there's any question, other lists
also have חזרת chazeret. at the top. The שמואל's Shmuel teaching,
the teaching from the house of שמואל Shmuel have חזרת chazeret at
the top. ואמר רבי אושעיא מצוה בחזרת, Ve-amar Rabbi Oshaya mitzvah be-chazeret,
and רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya made it explicit, the best one is
חזרת. chazeret? ואמר רבא, Ve-amar Rava, and now we're going to explain
why חזרת chazeret? is preferable, so this could easily be read as
the question of lettuce versus horseradish. Right? Do you go for something
that's a more powerful overwhelming taste might not even be bitter as
we've even been saying, or do you go for something that's a
little bit more subtle? But now what would be the preference of
חזרת? chazeret ואמר רבא: Ve-amar Rava: מאי חזרת? Mai chazeret? What's the
significance of חזרת? chazeret, So we know חזרת Chazeret is called חסא,
chasa which means lettuce. So חסא, so מאי חסא? Mai chasa? what's
the symbolism? דחס רחמנא עלן, De-chas Rachmana ilan, that God had רחמנות
rachmanas on us, חסא is compassion. Now, so funny 'cause that's not
normally
the identification of מרור maror of course, it is, when does God
hear? God hears when בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael finally cry out. So
anyway, but it
is interesting that they're using this completely as symbolic, which is okay
because basically the argument here could be that all bitter herbs are
equivalent fundamentally. So if they're all fundamentally equivalent, better to pick one
that has some type of additional symbolism. Why not get something that's
additionally symbolic? Which is very interesting in the context of the סדר.
Seder. It's not a surprise for us, but so much the סדר
Seder is this issue about using symbolism to tell a story. To
the point of course where it's become a little bit absurd nowadays
that everybody has to say their little דבר תורה dvar Torah at
the סדר Seder which often gets into these types of symbolisms which
are like והיא, ve-hi, שישה, shisha, ו vav is the שישה סדרי
משנה shisha sidrei Mishnah and חמישה chamisha is the חמישה חומשי תורה.
chamisha chumshei Torah. Like give me a break already. Okay, but the
idea that starts from a process where you use foods and you
use these symbolic ways of telling a story. So here it's saying
you might also pick a word that the name of that also
conveys some symbolism. Okay, and now we're not done, here's additional symbolism,
not just by the name, and something that more does connect to
the experience of eating it. ואמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי
יונתן: Ve-amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan: למה נמשלו מצרים
כמרור? Lama nimshelu Mitzrim ke-maror? Why were the מצרים Mitzrim compared to
מרור? maror, Now the מצרים Mitzrim were never compared to מרור, maror.
right? The work was וימררו את חייהם. va-yemararu et chayeihem. I mean
their actions were embittering, but okay. לומר לך, Lomer lach, to tell
you: מה מרור זה שתחלתו רך וסופו קשה, ma maror zeh she-tchilato
rach ve-sofo kasheh, the same way מרור maror starts off soft and
ends hard. Now רש"י Rashi says this actually just means the physical
plant, that like the stalk starts off softer and then it hardens.
Some want to read that it's also actually about the taste of
it. That the taste starts off meaning in the ground as it's
growing in the ground some say it means the taste of it
that like lettuce if we're talking specifically about lettuce it starts off
not having a bitter taste but after a while the leaves become
a little bit more bitter. So why is it that so the
same way that's true about this about מרור, maror. soft and then
becomes
hard, so אף מצרים תחלתן רכה וסופן קשה. af Mitzrim tchilatan rakah
ve-sofan kashah. Even the מצרים, Mitzrim, at first they were softer with
us and then they were harder, which might mean at first they
were very welcoming and then they were starting enslaving us, or even
within the process of enslaving. enslavement, right, it didn't start all overnight,
sort of like with Nuremberg and whatnot, they know that they did
it gradually and they duped the Jews into the בני ישראל Bnei
Yisrael into it until finally it became obviously extremely embittering. So that
is the additional symbolism and not just a name and why you
should prefer that rather than something that is very harsh like this
מרור. maror So again, that's a push for the more lettuce and
less the horseradish. אמר
ליה,
Amar
lei, so he said, הדר בי. hadri bi. Okay, I retract. It's
a good point, I'll start having the lettuce. Okay, אמר ליה רב
חומי לאביי, Amar lei Rav Chumi le'Abaye, רב חומי Rav Chumi said
to אביי, Abaye, ממאי דהאי מרור מין ירק הוא? mimai dehai מרור
maror min yerak hu? What makes us assume that this מרור maror
is a type of a vegetable? It just says something bitter. אימא
מרירתא דכופיא, eima merirta dechufya, maybe it's a type of a bitter
part of a fish? Okay, there's apparently a fish called כופיא chufya
and there was a bitter part of it, but who even says
it's a vegetable?
דומיא דמצה. Dumya dematzah. No, we assume it's similar to מצה. matzah
מה מצה גידולי קרקע, Ma matzah gidulei karka, the same way מצה
matzah comes from a plant, something that grows from the ground, אף
מרור גידולי קרקע, af maror gidulei karka, we'll assume the same by
the מרור. maror. ואימא הירדוף, Ve'eima hirdof, what about הירדוף, hirdof, which
is a type of a almost a poisonous spice? Now if it's
really poisonous you can't eat it, but רש״י Rashi says maybe it's
poisonous to animals. So he said, I'm sorry, no, I'm jumping ahead
to something else. הירדוף Hirdof is something else. But it is a
bitter tree, it's a part of a bark or a tree that's
bitter. So he said דומיא דמצה, dumya dematzah, similar to מצה. matzah.
מה מצה מין זרעים, Ma matzah min zera'im, the same way מצה
matzah is not a tree, it comes from wheat, which is you
plant a seed and something grows. Now of course trees also come
from seeds or acorns, but anyway, but still, it's different. Obviously it's
something you plant and cut down rather than something that grows over
many years. אף מרור מין זרעים, Af maror min zera'im, so מרור
maror, also is a type of comes from is a seed, a
plant of seeds. ואימא הירזיפו, Ve'eima hirzipu, maybe it's this הירזיפו, hirzipu,
which is that's the thing which is maybe somewhat poisonous at least
to animals. So דומיא דמצה, dumya dematzah, so it's a pretty amazing,
interesting thing that maybe you should use something somewhat poisonous. But דומיא
דמצה. dumya dematzah. מה מצה שניקחת בכסף מעשר, Ma matzah shenikachat bechesef
ma'aser, the same way מצה matzah, is enough of a food that
you would buy it with מעשר ma'aser money, אף מרור שניקח בכסף
מעשר. af maror shenikach bechesef ma'aser. It has to be something that's
normally edible, not something that's even if it's not poisonous to humans
is not really considered edible. It has to be an edible type
of a thing that you could buy it with מעשר ma'aser money,
which is a broad category of things that are considered things that
grow from the ground and are edible. Okay. So אמר ליה רבא
בר בר חנה לאביי, Amar lei Rava bar Bar Chana le'Abaye, so
that's how we know to focus on plants. אמר ליה רבא בר
בר חנה לאביי, Amar lei Rava bar Bar Chana le'Abaye, רבא בר
בר חנה Rava bar Bar Chana said to אביי, Abaye, אימא מרור
חד, eima maror chad, maybe there's only one species of plants? How
do you know to be a very general category? מרירים כתיב, meririm
ketiv, bitters it says, so bitters is a broader, it's a bigger
category. What are? In England they say bitters, right? What does that?
But they use that's some type of a thing that they drink,
right? No, what's bitters? It's right? Is it a drink? So what
is it? What type of a drink is it?
It's a beer? No, it's sort of like it's more bitter than
tonic water. It's, yeah.
Is it like a lemon type of a? No, it's
no, it's bitter. Bitter. I don't know the difference. Anyway, it's bitters
in the plural. ואימא מרירים תרי, Ve'eima meririm terei, maybe it's only
two types? So דומיא דמצה. dumya dematzah. No, similar to מצה. Matzah
מה מצה מינין הרבה, Ma matzah minin harbe, the same way מצה
Matzah. many types of grain can be used, אף מרור מינין הרבה,
af maror minin harbe, even מרור maror we say that many different
types of plants can satisfy. It's not one type of plant that's
called מרור.
maror But the basic question, I mean we never really prove that
you can have all these things for מצה, Matzah can we?
Right, that's all just tradition. Right. אמר רב הונא אמר רב, Amar
Rav Huna amar Rav, or it's identification of what's מחמיץ, machmitz, but
again the תורה Torah doesn't identify specific plants. It doesn't here either
identify specific plants. Okay. אמר רב הונא אמר רב, Amar Rav Huna
amar Rav, ירקות שאמרו חכמים שאדם יוצא בהן חובתו בפסח, Yerakot she'amru
chachamim she'adam yotzei vahen chovato bePesach, the things you fulfill your obligation
on פסח, pesach כולן נזרעין בערוגה אחת. kulan nizra'in be'aruga achat. They
can all be planted in one flower, like one vegetable bed, which
is a כלאים kilayim issue, which presumably he says that since they're
all called מרור, Maror they're all seen as the same type of
a related species of plant and there's no כלאים kilayim concern, which
is a little bit funny because you could certainly say that the
definitions of כלאים kilayim and different types of species, very different things
might have a bitter taste. So the גמרא Gemara is going to
challenge it. למימרא דלית בהו משום כלאים? Lemeimra delyt behu mishum kilayim?
You mean to say there's no כלאים kilayim concern? מתיב רבא, Metiv
Rava, so רבא Rava asked, here we have a משנה Mishnah in
כלאים: Kilayim: חזרת וחזרת גלים, Chazeret vechazeret galim, you can plant together
חזרת, Chazeret. whatever this type of a lettuce, and חזרת גלים, chazeret
galim, this other species of lettuce. Those with one another with each
other are not כלאים. kilayim. They're the same type of category. עולשין
ועולשי שדה, Ulshin ve'ulshei sadeh, the same about
עולשין and
the wild and domesticated presumably of this endive. כרישין וכרישי שדה, Kerishin
ve'kerishei sadeh, similarly about leeks
and wild leeks. כוסבר וכוסבר שדה, Kusbar ve'kusbar sadeh,
חרדל וחרדל מצרי. chardal ve'chardal mitzri. Okay or... mustard or Egyptian mustard,
ודלעת המצרי והרמוצה ve'Dila'at ha'Mitzri ve'ha'Ramuza and this Egyptian gourd and רמוצה.
Harmuza. All of these
pairs אינם כלאים זה בזה. einam Kilayim ze be'ze. So those every
two of them are the same species and are not כלאים Kilayim
if you plant the two of them together. So the גמרא Gemara
says חזרת וחזרת גלין אין, Chazeret ve'Chazeret Galin in, so חזרת Chazeret.
you can plant together with חזרת גלין, Chazeret Galin, these two types
of lettuce. חזרת ועולשין לא, Chazeret ve'Oulshin lo, but not lettuce and
endives? So you see only these pairs are okay, not to mix
different types of things. וכי תימא כולהו בהדדי קתני להו, Ve'chi teima
kulhu behadadi katani lehu, let's say you choose to read this משנה
Mishnah not that way, you say no, everything mentioned in this משנה
Mishnah can all be planted together, which would be very funny because
the משנה Mishnah very clearly reads in pairs. So he says no,
ואמר רב זוגות זוגות קתני, Ve'amar Rav zugot zugot katani, Rav said
the משנה Mishnah? is to be read as pairs, that each pair
is okay, but not that you can mix everything together. So clearly
these different things, nobody is arguing that they are the same species,
they're just saying they all are bitter and therefore they're all okay,
but not that they're the same species. So the גמרא Gemara says
fine. מאי נזרעים דאמר רב, Mai nizra'im de'amar Rav, so when Rav
says they can all be planted together, what does he mean, planted
together? דאמר רב נזרעים כהלכתן, De'amar Rav nizra'im ke'hilchatan, that they can
be planted like you would normally be allowed to plant five different
species
of plants in the same square because we've seen this before, there's
this thing that if you have a flower bed that is six
by six טפחים, tefachim, you can plant five species of plants. Now
how do you do that is debated, some say what it means
is you do it like this, so they don't touch at the
corners and you get four, and then the fifth one you do
here like that, or some say the fifth one you do like
this, so because, and again even though they're close, because of the
shapes they're clearly separate from one another, or some say you do
just the corners like this and one in the middle. But anyway
those things are debated, but there's different ways in which in one
space of six by six טפחים, tefachim, which is not big, it's
two feet by two feet, you're allowed to plant five different types
of plants in a way in which visually or by distance it
would prevent it from becoming כלאים. Kilayim. So then what's the big
חידוש? chiddush? So let's keep on reading. So the גמרא Gemara says
כהלכתן, ke'hilchatan, if you're doing it the normal way תנינא, tenina, so
we've already taught that. What do we teach in a משנה Mishnah,
in כלאים? Kilayim? ערוגה
שהיא ששה על ששה טפחים, Aruga she'hi shisha al shisha tefachim, if
you have a vegetable bed that's six by six טפחים, tefachim, זורעין
בתוכה חמשה זרעונין, zorin betocha chamisha zeronin,
you can plant five different types of seeds. ארבע על ארבע רוחות
הערוגה, Arba al arba ruchot ha'aruga, four by the four directions, sides,
ואחת באמצע, ve'achat ba'emtza,
and one in the middle. So what are you telling me, it's
a משנה? Mishnah No, מהו דתימא הני מילי בזרעים, Mahu deteima hani
mili bezra'im, I might have thought that that's only by seeds, meaning
things like
grain. אבל בירקות, Aval beyerakot, but by vegetables, לא, I might have
thought that maybe vegetables are more
problematic, maybe they draw nutrients from a greater distance because part of
the problem of כלאים Kilayim is visual, but
part of the problem of כלאים Kilayim is that they're seen as
drawing nutrients from one another. So maybe vegetables are different than grains.
קמשמע לן Kamashma lan that vegetables are no different. So the גמרא
Gemara says למימרא דירקות אלימי מזרעים? Lemeimra de'yerakot alimi mizra'im? What, you
mean to tell me that vegetables would be stronger? Stronger doesn't here
mean better, more problematic is what it means, draws more powerfully than
seeds? והתנן, Ve'hatnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah כל מיני זרעים
אין נזרעים בערוגה אחת, Kol minei zra'im ein nizra'im ba'aruga achat,
if you deal with seeds meaning things again like let's say grains,
that cannot be in one bed like we discussed. כל מיני ירקות
נזרעים בערוגה אחת, Kol minei yerakot nizra'im ba'aruga achat, but all different
types of vegetables can all be if you follow the right configuration
in this one type
of a square.
So you see that actually vegetables are better than seeds. So again,
the משנה Mishnah is quite clear you could have five in this
six by six square, it's clear you could do it by vegetables,
if what is the חידוש chiddush telling me that this applies to
the מרור Maror category? Quick question. So wait, let's just read the
answer. So the גמרא Gemara says מהו דתימא, mahu deteima,
no, I might have thought הני מרור מין זרעים נינהו, hani maror
min zra'im ninhu, maybe I would have thought that the things that
are called מרור marors? are not vegetables but they're more these seed
things which I don't know exactly, again I've been translating זרעים zra'im
as grains because for me, I don't know, maybe seeds are, I
don't know what is other than vegetables?
I guess vegetables grow from seeds, everything, I mean
everything grows from seeds. That was what I was going to ask,
this is an interesting linguistic distinction. Like when we say סדר זרעים,
Seder Zeraim, should we properly understand that to mean the הלכות halachot
of grains and אגב גרירא agav grira other agricultural produce?
Yeah, I don't know, I don't think that what the גמרא Gemara
is using here to distinguish זרעים zra'im from ירקות yerakot. has to
be assumed that that's always... is the mean of זרעים. Zeraim. But
here in context, my understanding of זרעים Zeraim here is that it
is types of grains, and then to think that I would have
thought that מרור Maror, are in that... are grains, and therefore, I
mean, you know, and therefore it has to tell me that you
plant them all the same to tell me they're in the vegetable
category. To me, that's pretty obvious. So, you know, I mean, who
thinks that מרור Maror? are grains, especially once they've been identified. So
maybe זרעים Zeraim maybe means... you can't do grains but anyway maybe
זרעים Zeraim here means something else. Anyway, let's read it and then
קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, so that therefore it teaches me
that. That these are not זרעים, Zeraim, they're ירקות. yerakot Okay, and
therefore they can be in the same thing. So the גמרא Gemara
says זרעים סלקא דעתך, Zeraim salka dach, what? You could have... how
could you have thought that they were type of זרעים? Zeraim? והתנן
ירקות, Vehatnan yerakot, the משנה Mishnah says these are the ירקות yerakot.
that you fulfill your obligation with. The משנה mishna lists them as
vegetables.
ותני בר קפרא ירקות, Vetani Bar Kappara yerakot, and when בר קפרא
Bar Kappara lists them, he teach... he says these are the vegetables.
ותני דבי שמואל ירקות, Vetani devei Shmuel yerakot, and when שמואל's Shmuel
ברייתא braita teaches it, it says ירקות. No, חזרת איצטריכא ליה. Chazeret
itztircha lei. The one thing that was unclear was חזרת. Chazeret? Okay.
סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka dach amina, I would have thought... because you're
right, forget the idea that I would have thought that they were
seeds and not vegetables. I know they're vegetables. So here's the only
issue why you had to tell me that it's okay for... for
כלאים kilayim purpose, because of חזרת. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka dach amina,
I would have thought הואיל וסופו להקשות. hoil vesofo lehakshot. Since as
we mentioned, what's special about חזרת? That it gets hard, and presumably
that also means that it gets thicker. Okay. So since it gets
harder and thicker as it stays in the ground, נסיב ליה רווחא
טפי, nasiv lei revacha tfei, so we need to give it more
space. It's not like any other vegetable. Maybe it really gets, you
know, thick and large, and therefore we give... need to give it
more space than we give other vegetables to prevent כלאים. kilayim.
Does that really happen?
It gets bigger? Apparently. I don't know. קא משמע לן, ka mashma
lan, so therefore it's telling me that you don't. Okay,
I'm sorry, I skipped a lot. נסיב ליה רווחא טפי. nasiv lei
revacha tfei. לאו אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, Lav amar Rabbi Yossi
b'Rabbi Chanina, didn't רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Chanina say
קלח של כרוב, klach shel kruv, the stalk of a cabbage... not
כרוב, kruv, yes, כרוב kruv a cabbage. What is כרוב? kruv? Yeah,
cabbage. Okay, שקשה, shekashah, that
if it once gets thick and hard, מרחיבין לו בית רובע, marchivin
lo beit rova, you give it the space of a בית רובע,
beit rova, you give it more space to get out of כלאים
kilayim concern. אלמא כיון דסופו להקשות יהבינן ליה רווחא טפי. Alma keivan
desofo lehakshot yehavinan lei revacha tfei.
You see by the cabbage if it's gonna get hard, you need
to give it more space. הכא נמי נסיב ליה רווחא טפי, Hacha
nami nasiv lei revacha tfei, maybe here too the same. קא משמע
לן, ka mashma lan, that you don't. It doesn't exactly help me
what make... to tell me what makes this different. Because what makes
it different that... I don't know. That it's not... that it only
happens after a long period of time? You don't have to worry
about it? That it's not as thick, or doesn't... doesn't really... yeah,
I really... I really can't tell you. It's a good... all I
can say is it's a good thing you're not learning כלאים. kilayim.
Okay, anyway, so that's the end of that discussion. That it did
seem the גמרא Gemara. initially wanted to say they're all one species,
but in the end, because of the pushback, made it a much
tamer statement.
So apparently you can't use a cabbage, right? Even though it's pale
green and is cabbage considered bitter? I don't think so.
I don't know. Cabbage? I don't know.
If it gets any more bitter than lettuce? Or no less bitter?
I really don't know. יוצאים בהם בין לחים בין יבשים. Yotzin bahen
bein lachim bein yeveshim. Now whether moist or dried. אמר רב חסדא,
Amar Rav Chisda, says רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, לא שנו אלא בקלח.
lo shanu ela bekelach. When is it that you can have dried
parts of these מרור? Maror Only if it's the stalk has been
dried. אבל בעלין, Aval bealin, if the leaves are dried, לחים אין
יבשים לא. lachim in yeveshim lo. Only moist, not dried. Because a
dried leaf is basically tasteless. So the only thing that's dried that's
okay is if it's a dried stalk. So the
גמרא Gemara says: והא קתני סיפא. veha katani seifa. The end of
the משנה mishna says: ובקלח שלהן. uvakelach shelahen. First it says you
fulfill the obligation with them whether they're moist or... or dried, and
then and you fulfill the obligation with their stalk. So it sounds
like in the beginning when we said moist or dried, we were
referring to their leaves, because we only introduced stalk later. מכלל דרישא
עלין, Michlal dereisha alin, it sounds like the beginning we're talking about
their leaves, and we're saying whether... whether moist or dried. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, פירושא קמפרש. perusha kamafarnish. It's... it's explaining itself.
כי קתני בין לחים בין יבשים אקלח. Ki katani bein lachim bein
yeveshim aklach. When that... that it says you fulfill your obligation with
them whether they're moist or dried, and then when it says "and
with their stalk," what it means is whether they're moist or dried,
if we're talking about their stalk. So that's a little bit of
a hard read, but that's at least the argument in the גמרא
Gemara that if the leaves are dried, they're not considered... really they
don't have any taste. Okay. מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'll ask you on this:
יוצאין בהן ובקלח שלהן. yotzin bahen uvakelach shelahen. This is a ברייתא.
braita. You fulfill your obligation with them and with or with their
stalk. בין לחים בין יבשים, Bein lachim bein yeveshim, whether moist or
dried. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says. So it sounds like he's saying moist dried is going
on בהן ובקלח שלהן, bahen uvakelach shelahen, them and their stalk. So
it also applies to them, it applies to the leaves.
וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, so we'll get back to that, but first
let's see the debate. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says whether moist or
dried. וחכמים אומרים לחים יוצאין בהן יבשים אין יוצאין בהן. Vachachamim omrim
lachim yotzin bahen yeveshim ein yotzin bahen. Only moist you fulfill your
obligation with them, dried you don't. ושוין שיוצאין בהן כמושין, Veshavin sheyotzin
bahen kemushin, they agree that if it's wilted, that's okay. By the
way, wilted is clearly something that happens to leaves, not to stalks.
Okay, so when the רבנן rabbanan say dried... dry is no good,
they're talking about the about dry. But wilted is still okay.
Wait, isn't it wilted because it's dry?
Well, it's not fully dried out. It's starting to get dry. It's
a middle category between לחין and יבש yavesh is כמוש, kamush, is
wilted. But לא כבושים lo kevushim and they also agree that you
cannot do pickled ולא שלוקים v'lo shlukim or double boiled ולא מבושלים
or boiled. כללו של דבר klalo shel davar the general rule is
כל שיש בו טעם מרור kol sheyesh bo taam maror now it
seems here that this line is not referring to the types of
vegetables although maybe it is also, but it's saying once you've identified
the vegetable as long as it still has the bitter taste, יוצאין
בו yotzin bo so you can fulfill your obligation. כל שאין בו
טעם מרור אין יוצאין בו kol she'ein bo taam maror ein yotzin
bo when it doesn't have the bitter taste because of the way
it's been processed or it's dried out you cannot fulfill your obligation.
Anyway you see that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says dried, he's
saying it even on the leaves. So the גמרא Gemara says תרגומא
אקלח targuma aklach no he's not talking about the leaves, he's talking
about the stalk. Again a very hard read because then why are
the Rabbis saying oh well we'll admit that wilted are okay? You
can have a wilted stalk? So I don't understand. It does seem
very clear that we are referring to leaves, but the גמרא gemara
insists that nobody would say dry leaves are okay and we're talking
only about the stalks. Yes.
Dry leaves actually have a stronger flavor because they're more concentrated.
Oh that's interesting.
That's why you buy oregano. Oregano's an example, yeah.
Aha. Would it be true about the bitter aspect of the flavor?
Like if you took a lettuce leaf and dried it out you
would still taste something bitter?
I've never tried it.
Okay. But it's a good question.
But it's certainly the case for coriander.
Alright so it's a very good question, I don't know. Okay, I
don't know. Look the simple sense of these משניות Mishnas and ברייתות
Braisas clearly is that the dry refers to the leaves.
Of course the שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch goes with this.
Yeah, yeah. Right, because that's the גמרא gemara you know defends it
and nobody says something and nobody takes an opposing position. תנו רבנן
tanu rabbanan אין יוצאין בהם כמושים ein yotzin bahem kemushim you now
we have a ברייתא Braisa that says that you cannot fulfill the
obligation if it is wilted. משום רבי אלעזר בר צדוק אמרו יוצאין
בהם כמושים mishum rabbi elazar bar tzadok amru yotzin bahem kemushim yes
wilted is okay, which is what we read before. בעי רמי בר
חמא ba'ei rami bar chama רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama asks
מהו שיצא אדם ידי חובתו במרור של מעשר שני בירושלים mahu sheyeitzei
adam yedei chovato bemaror shel ma'aser sheni b'yerushalayim ah we were so
afraid we were not we were too much about practical questions, so
thank God we get back to this issue about מעשר שני Ma'aser
Sheni in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, can you fulfill your obligation? Now remember
מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni. in ירושלים Yerushalayim you're allowed to eat it,
but the issue was by מצה Matzah that we learned from the
פסוק Pasuk of בכל מושבותיכם bechol moshvoteichem it has to be able
to be eaten anywhere. So מרור, Maror same thing maybe. מעשר שני
Ma'aser Sheni in ירושלים Yerushalayim can only be eaten in ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
Is that okay? So that was a debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva and רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosi HaGlili by
מצה. Matzah Since were it to become טמא tamei you could redeem
it so in theory you could eat it elsewhere. רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva said it's okay. What if the same happened to מרור? Maror
אליבא דרבי עקיבא לא תיבעי לך aliba de'rabbi akiva lo tiba'i lach
according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva I have no question. השתא במצה
דאורייתא נפיק hashta bematzah d'oraisa nafik you fulfill your obligation with מצה
Matzah which is דאורייתא, d'oraisa, במרור דרבנן מיבעיא bemaror derabbanan mibaya certainly
it would be okay which is מרור Maror which is only rabbinic.
I'm going to get back to biblical and rabbinic in a minute,
let me just finish reading the גמרא. gemara כי
תיבעי לך ki tiba'i lach what's my question to you אליבא דרבי
יוסי הגלילי aliba de'rabbi yosi haglili according to רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi
Yosi HaGlili that says מצה Matzah is no good if it's מעשר
שני Ma'aser Sheni in ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
מאי mai what would you say? במצה דאורייתא הוא דלא נפיק bematzah
d'oraisa hu dela nafik מצה Matzah which is דאורייתא, d'oraisa, that's where
he says you can't fulfill your
obligation, אבל מרור דרבנן נפיק aval maror derabbanan nafik fulfill, או דילמא
כל דתיקון רבנן כעין דאורייתא תיקון o dilma kol detikkun rabbanan ke'ein
d'oraisa tikkun anything that's rabbinic we make it like it's biblical so
we would give it the same status as מצה Matzah and if
מצה Matzah is no good מרור Maror is no good. אמר רבא
amar rava so רבא Rava said מסתברא מצה מרור mistavra matzah maror
makes sense that we put מצה Matzah and מרור Maror in the
same category, they're connected מצות ומרורים matzos u'merorim we learned that before,
right we learned that מרור Maror like מצה Matzah that it has
to be a type of a plant and it has to be
a food and different types of things. So here too we learn
that if מצה Matzah is no good according to רבי יוסי הגלילי,
Rabbi Yosi HaGlili, מרור Maror is also no good if it's מעשר
שני. Ma'aser Sheni Now, what does the גמרא Gemara mean biblical versus
rabbinic? Thoughts?
בזמן הזה bazman hazeh
okay it means nowadays says Michael, that certainly the phrase מצה דאורייתא
matzah d'oraisa means the obligation of מצה Matzah is דאורייתא, d'oraisa, the
obligation of מרור Maror is rabbinic, because מרור Marror is only with
the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, מצה Matza exists as an independent obligation
and it exists even nowadays. Okay that's one possibility. רש"י Rashi does
not like that. I'll tell you why he doesn't like that in
a minute. And רש"י Rashi says no, מצה דאורייתא matzah d'oraisa means
that the מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni is דאורייתא, d'oraisa, because מצה Matza
is from grain and the obligation to take מעשר Ma'aser from grain
is biblical, whereas מרור Marror. the status of מעשר Ma'aser is only
rabbinic because the whole obligation to take תרומות ומעשרות from vegetables is
purely rabbinic. So it's entire מעשר שני status is a weaker status,
it's only a rabbinic status and therefore maybe says the גמרא Gemara
it should not be as much of an issue for רבי יוסי
הגלילי. Rabbi Yosi HaGlili. It's not like rabbinic טבל tevel where it's
forbidden to be eaten. It's permissible to be eaten, it's in ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, but the whole status is rabbinic, so therefore maybe we would
go easier. That's what רש"י Rashi says. Now why doesn't he like
what Michael said? When you say מצה דאורייתא matzah d'oraisa you think
you're talking about the obligation of
מצה Matza is
דאורייתא d'oraisa and מרור Marror is... at a time when there is
a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Now we could argue maybe even after
the חורבן הבית Churban HaBayis there's קדושה Kedusha and you have to
eat it in ירושלים Yerushalayim and so on but רש"י Rashi says
if that's much more complicated and we should have said that. The
simple sense if we're talking about מעשר שני in ירושלים Yerushalayim is
at the time of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So therefore רש"י
Rashi does not choose to read the גמרא as דאורייתא d'Oraisa דרבנן
d'Rabbanan about the time of about nowadays but דאורייתא d'Oraisa דרבנן d'Rabbanan
about the obligation of מעשר by vegetables. Now I want to make
a point about that which is that according to רש"י Rashi therefore
right and we should have realized this ourselves we're talking about מעשר
in ירושלים Yerushalayim and whatever. We're talking about the time of the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So then it becomes doubly ironic because we
pointed out this need to be able to be eaten בכל מושבותיכם
bechol moshvosechem is a little interesting since the paradigmatic מצה Matza in
the תורה Torah is eaten together with the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach.
So according to רש"י here I am in ירושלים Yerushalayim eating my
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and I'm eating it with מצה Matza and
מרור Marror of מעשר שני which has to be eaten in ירושלים
Yerushalayim and my קרבן פסח Korban Pesach has to be eaten in
ירושלים Yerushalayim so maybe I'm fulfilling my obligation of על מצות ומרורים
יאכלוהו al matzos umerorim yochluhu about the מצה Matza you know but
I'm not fulfilling my obligation of מצה Matza because the מצה Matza
is not בכל מושבותיכם. bechol moshvosechem. But what's also weird saying then
is I'm also not fulfilling my obligation not just of מצה Matza
but what did we just say also not my obligation of מרור.
Marror But the מרור Marror is only something isn't an independent מצוה
mitzva right nowadays we do it its Rabbinic it's to remember the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach right but the מרור Marror is only a
מצוה mitzva of eating the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach with מרור Marror
and according to this the way רש"י understands this גמרא I don't
fulfill my biblical obligation of eating my קרבן פסח Korban Pesach which
could only be eaten in ירושלים Yerushalayim with the מרור Marror the
מרור Marror part I haven't fulfilled if the מרור Marror is limited
to ירושלים Yerushalayim if the מרור Marror can't be taken out of
ירושלים Yerushalayim it's very bizarre.
Okay but it's only Rabbinically you can't take it out of ירושלים.
Yerushalayim.
Well that besides the Rabbinic but conceptually the idea that not only
for the independent מצוה mitzva of מצה Matza does it have to
be able to be eaten everywhere but for the מצוה mitzva of
מצה Matza and מרור Marror that come with the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach that it it's it's not good if it's limited to ירושלים
Yerushalayim even though the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach itself is limited to
ירושלים Yerushalayim that is a very strange idea but it does make
us think about when we're talking about מצה Matza and מרור Marror?
are we talking about them as independent מצוות mitzvos or are we
talking about them as the accompaniment to the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
and I want to make another point about that. Our משנה mishna
says right you you a כזית kezayis. you get a כזית kezayis
of מרור Marror you know you get a little bit from all
things and you get a כזית. kezayis According to the תורה Torah
when I am doing my מצוה mitzva of על מצות ומרורים יאכלוהו
al matzos umerorim yochluhu I have here my קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
and I have a little מרור Marror thrown in do I need
a כזית kezayis of מרור? Marror Normally I need a כזית kezayis
if the תורה Torah says you must eat מצה Matza you must
eat this okay or to transgress eating X I have to eat
a כזית kezayis to say I did an act of eating this
thing. But when the תורה Torah says על מצות ומרורים יאכלוהו al
matzos umerorim yochluhu it's telling me the מצוה mitzva of eating is
eating the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach right the מצה Matza and the
מרור Marror. are just like accompaniments and if there's some מרור Marror
with it presumably I've done my מצוה mitzva and according to a
number of ראשונים Rishonim to fulfill the מצוה mitzva of מרור Marror
biblically with your קרבן פסח Korban Pesach you don't need a כזית
kezayis. of מרור. Marror What happens is that Rabbinically once we have
made it an independent מצוה mitzva nowadays so we eat מרור Marror
by itself and we don't eat it with the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach now Rabbinically it becomes a מצוה mitzva to eat מרור Marror
and it needs a כזית kezayis because it's a standalone מצוה mitzva
of eating. But in the תורה it's part of the קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach and doesn't need but our משנה mishna though mentions a
כזית. So really the simple sense and let me also point out
we have a משנה mishna about מצה Matza we have a משנה
mishna about מרור Marror the next משנה mishna, is going back to
חמץ chametz what don't we have a משנה mishna about?
Eating the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Now there's going to be like
a couple of פרקים prakim about the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach but
nevertheless the fact that we identify מצה matzah and מרור Marror and
talk about a כזית of מרור Marror and so on and we
don't talk about the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach makes it sound not
like רש"י that we are talking about nowadays the standalone מצוה mitzva
of מצה matzah and מרור Marror and not the מרור Marror that
accompany the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach okay and then it makes a
little more sense that we have this idea that it has to
be able to be eaten out of ירושלים Yerushalayim as well. But
that's just to to focus you on this issue about what do
we mean by the מצוה mitzva of מרור maror. two very different
types of things.
Okay yeah but you gave me an idea you know even the
תנאים Tannaim saw in the מצה matzah itself
two opposing meanings of לחם עוני lechem oni, and לחם גאולה. Lechem
Ge'ula.
Right exactly.
So now you've got the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach required to be
together with the מרור maror you might gain the same type of
duality that the מרור maror. is לתקן. litakain. the אוכל, ochel,
but it's also לגנאי. lignai.
Right. But it actually does something sort of, you know, it's a
nice accompaniment to that. Right.
But it might also, but it has that negative aspect to it
as well. Right.
I actually, that's true, I actually, and this is for maybe another
time, but I actually think that in the Torah, the מצה matzah
of על מצות ומרורים functions as a type of a מרור. The
גאולה geula is the קרבן פסח, korban pesach, right? The פסח is
what signifies the גאולה. geula. The מצה matzah. is the לחם עוני,
lechem oni, the same way the מרור is וימררו את חייהם. vayimararu
et chayeihem. Nowadays that we don't have a קרבן פסח, korban pesach,
the מצה matzah starts with הא לחמא עניא די אכלו אבהתנא ha
lachma anya di achlu avatana with לחם עוני, but then it transforms
to symbolize the גאולה geula and it becomes the substitute for the
קרבן פסח. korban pesach. But that's when we don't have a קרבן
פסח. korban pesach. I think that when we did have the קרבן
פסח, korban pesach, the מצה had just the symbolism of, right, of
the
embitterment. Anyway, but yes, it is important to note that dual nature
of the מצה. Let's start now the next משנה, and I have
no idea why in the middle of one and a half פרקים
prakim beforehand that was all about getting rid of your חמץ chametz,
and about not eating and getting הנאה hana'ah from your חמץ, chametz
and the next one and a half פרקים prakim that are all
going to be about חמץ chametz concerns, why smack in the middle
we had these two משניות mishnayot about מצה and מרור. It was
a nice break, but
I don't understand the organization, and now with this משנה we get
back to חמץ chametz. discussion. So let's take a look. אין שורין
את המורסן לתרנגולים. ein shorin et hamursan letarnagolim. You do not sort
of, you know, submerge in water the מורסן, mursan, which is, what
does it say מורסן mursan is, bran? Bran.
Bran. In water because as feed for your chickens, because obviously you
submerge it in water, it's going to become חמץ. chametz So don't
think that just if you're making bread you have a חמץ chametz.
issue. Any contact of water with these flowers or with these grains.
אבל חולטין aval choltin what you can do is you can scald
it, and we discussed this earlier when we discussed חלוט. chalut. That
if you put grain or flour in scalding water, in boiling water,
it'll cook it and prevent it from becoming from
fermenting. האשה לא תשרה את המורסן שתוליך בידה למרחץ. haisha lo tishreh
et hamursan shetolich beyada lemerchatz. Again, interesting when it introduces women based
on the realities it saw in their society. So a woman, they
would have like these types
of things that they would put on their skin, you know, people
sometimes put mud on their face or different types of things. So
they would do these things, I don't know, for moisturizing. So they
would put bran in water and then put it on their skin.
So she cannot do that to take with her to the bathhouse,
אבל, because then it's going to become חמץ. chametz שפה היא בבשרה
יבש. shafah hi bivsarah yavesh. Once her skin is dry, she can
rub the bran against the skin once the skin is dry, but
you can't get it wet. לא ילעוס אדם, lo yilous adam, and
a person, again here meaning a man presumably, but really any person,
cannot chew חיטים, chitim, you know, chew wheat, ויניח על מכתו, veyaniach
al makato, and put that as a type of some type of
a poultice or salve on his wound, מפני שמחמיצות. mipnei shemachmizot.
All these things coming in contact with water and leaving them around
and not baking them create חמץ chametz: concerns.
Wait, does
חלוט chalut mean boiling water? Yeah. So you're telling me like if
you put oats in boiling water?
Technically that is okay.
The שלחן ערוך
shulchan aruch says nobody does this now, we don't trust anybody to
do this properly. But technically speaking you could
make oatmeal on
Pesach?
Technically speaking. תנו רבנן. tano rabanan. Our Rabbis taught, let's read a
line about this. אלו דברים שאין באין לידי חימוץ. elu devarim she'ein
ba'in lidei chimutz. The following things don't become חמץ: chametz. האפוי, ha'afuy,
if you've already baked it, so there goes גברוקס gebrokts concerns. If
you've baked it, you're okay. והמבושל, vehamivushal, or if you cooked it,
וחלוט, vechalut, or if you scalded it, שחלטו ברותחים, shechalato berotchim, the
water was already boiling and you threw it into the water or
you poured the water on it. So now the גמרא says, מבושל,
mivushal, cooked? So it means if your cooking is contrasted to the
water's already boiling, you put it in the water before it gets
fully hot and then you're cooking it. So the גמרא says, אדמבשל
ליה מחמע. ad demivashil lei machma. By the time it cooks, it's
had time to ferment, right, because if you put it in the
water before the water was boiling hot, it's had time to ferment.
So אמר רב פפא, amar rav pappa, האפוי שבישלו קאמר. ha'afuy shebishlo
ka'amar. No, what we mean is if it's already been baked, then
cooking it is not a problem. But you're right, to just slow
cook it would be a problem. But basically he says the entire
ברייתא braita is actually talking about גברוקס. gebrokts. You have something baked,
you now cook it in water, no problem. Okay. תניא, tanya, we
learned a ברייתא, braita, רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה אומר, rabi yose
bar rabi yehuda omer, קמח שנפל לתוכו דלף. kemach shenafal letocho delef.
If you have flour that's falling into it was like a dripping
of water, drip, drip, drip, אפילו כל היום כולו, afilu kol hayom
kulo, אינו בא לידי חימוץ. eino ba lidei chimutz. The fact that
there's constant stuff hitting it, that prevents fermenting. The same way the
גמרא understands that if you're kneading the dough and constantly working it,
it doesn't ferment, if water is constantly dripping on it, it doesn't
ferment. So אמר רב פפא, amar rav pappa, והוא דעביד טיף לחדי
טיף. vehu de'avid tip latchada tip. That's only when it goes drip,
drip, drip, drip, drip, like there's no stopping. You also wonder like
What if the drip is hitting one location, other parts might get
wet that doesn't have the drip hitting it. So, anyway, אמר דבי
רבי שילא, Amar de'vei Rabbi Sheila, וטיקא שרי. vatika shari. וטיקא's Vatika
allowed, okay. So רשי says it's a certain type of a flour
food, you know, food based on flour made from flour. So the
גמרא says ותניא וטיקא אסור. vatanya vatika assur. We taught that that's
forbidden. לא קשיא. Lo kashya. הא דעבדי במשחא ומלחא, Ha de'avdi b'mishcha
milcha, one is you didn't use any water, you just used oil
and salt. So again, oil without water is not a problem of
חמץ. chametz, מי פירות אין מחמיצין, Mei peirot ein machmitzin, although there's
different opinions about that. הא דעבדי במיא ומלחא, Ha de'avdi b'maya milcha,
and the other is you used water, but if you didn't use
any water, you just used oil, you're okay. אמר מר זוטרא, Amar
Mar Zutra, and this is the last line. Remember we had just
said essentially before that געבראכטס gebrochts is okay. But אמר מר זוטרא,
Amar Mar Zutra, לא למחו איניש קדירה בקמחא דאבישנא. lo limchei inish
kedeira b'kimcha d'avishna. A person should not thicken their pot, like you're
making a soup and throw in flour to make it thicker, with
grain that has been like roasted, with roasted
grain, even though we said before that if stuff's already been baked,
you know, it can't become חמץ, chametz. don't use roasted grain to
thicken your soup. Why not? דילמא לא בשיל שפיר. Dilma lo bishal
shapir. Maybe you did not roast the grain sufficiently. ואתי לידי חימוץ.
V'ati lidei chimutz. And now you put it in your soup and
it will become חמץ. chametz, And that is the reason for געבראכטס.
gebrochts. The concern of געבראכטס gebrochts is, yes, technically if it's been
baked it can't become חמץ, chametz. but maybe there are little pieces
of flour that haven't been baked and you put it into your
soup and it'll become חמץ. So in this גמרא you see exactly
the געבראכטס gebrochts issue. The actual הלכה halacha is there's no concern
of געבראכטס, gebrochts, but there are times where maybe it's a concern,
maybe you didn't bake it well enough. Okay. Just fine. And with
that, yeah, but it's been baked, it's been roasted. Okay, more about
this tomorrow.